Finding Aid for the Lamoni Call Papers LSC.1158
UCLA Library Special Collections
Lamoni Call papers
1898-1926
UCLA Library Special Collections
Call, Lamoni
LSC.1158
2.5 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
Lamoni Call (b.1865) was a dissenter from the Mormon faith. He published various pamphlets questioning Mormon beliefs, including Science and Mormonism (1926). The collection consists of Call's correspondence, manuscripts, notes, books, and memoranda. Almost all the items relate to his research and writings on Mormonism.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Dortha C. Causey, 1975.
Gift of Ardith Call Kreis, 1975.
Gift of La Mar A. Call, 1975.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9973814823606533
We are committed to providing ethical, inclusive, and anti-racist description of the materials we steward, and to remediating existing description of our materials that contains language that may be offensive or cause harm. We invite you to submit feedback about how our collections are described, and how they could be described more accurately, by filling out the form located on our website: Report Potentially Offensive Description in Library Special Collections.
Biography
Call was born in 1865; he lived in Bountiful and Salt Lake City, Utah, and was a dissenter from the Mormon faith; published various pamphlets questioning Mormon beliefs, including Science and Mormonism (1926).
Scope and Content
Collection consists of correspondence, manuscripts, notes, books, and memoranda of Lamoni Call, a dissenter from the Mormon faith. Almost all the items relate to his research and writings on Mormonism and the various pamphlets he published questioning Mormon beliefs.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Correspondence (Box 1).
Manuscripts, notes and memoranda (Boxes 1-2).
Printed items by Lamoni Call (Box 2).
Printed items marked or annotated by Lamoni Call (Boxes 2-4).
Unmarked items (Box 4).
Periodicals (Box 5).
Mormon Church; Mormons.; Manuscripts for publication; Dissenters, Religious -- Utah -- Archives.; Call, Lamoni--Archives.
- Correspondence, 1921-1933 and n.d.; (4 folders)
  - From Lamoni Call to Emerson and Fern Call, 1921-25 and n.d.; (5 letters) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Between Lamoni Call and various persons re Mormonism, 1923-33, and n.d.; (13 letters) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - From O.J. Call to Lamoni Call, 1926; (2 letters) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Between Lamoni Call and the Freethought Press Association, 1932-33; (6 letters, 2 envelopes) (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Manuscripts, Notes and Memoranda, 1884[?]-1925 and n.d.; (53 folders)
  - "An address to the Latter-Day Saints", (4 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Antiquities", n.d.; (11 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Apparitions. The Writer's Experience", (3 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Book of Mormon antiquities", (43 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Book of Mormon history", (21 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Book of Mormon history. Unreasonable and impossible", (37 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "The Book of Mormon - prophetic evidence, and prophecy plain", (38 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Book of Mormon. Translation", (42 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Constructive or destructive", (4 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Contradictions", (13 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Cover tinted with Argument", (2 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "Doctrine", (18 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Do Mormon leaders dictate to their members in political matters?", ( 3 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "The eighteenth amendment", (5 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "Faith", (43 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "Faith: Gospel faith from a Mormon point of view", (7 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "The good join the church", n.d.; (2 different copies, each 7 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "A heart to heart talk with my Mormon friends", (2 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "High spots", (5 pieces) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "How did Joseph Smith receive revelations?", (21 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "The hub", (7 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - "Is it the duty of government to look after individuals?", (7 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - "Is Mormonism a religion?", (3 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - "Joseph Smith's early life", (20 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - "Joseph Smith's word", 2 different copies, each 11 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - "Let us get acquainted", (3 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - "Manner of translating the Book of Mormon", (56 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - "The Mormon god", n.d.; (6 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - "Mormon god; Mormon hell; & Fell to the earth", n.d.; (29 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - "The Mormon heaven", n.d.; (7 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - "The Mormon hell", n.d.; (9 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - "Mormon persecution", n.d.; (105 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - "Mormon polygamy: introduction", n.d.; (5 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - "Mormon testimony", n.d.; (2 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - "Mormonism is admittedly wrong by about sixty percent of the people of Utah", July 25, 1925; (2 leaves) (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - "Mormonism unravelled", 1924; (2 different copies) (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - (2 pieces) (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - "Mormonism. Well? What of it? Just this", n.d.; (5 leaves) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "The murderous knights of Columbus", n.d.; (3 leaves) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Pre-existence of spirits", n.d.; (10 leaves) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "Prophecy plain", n.d.; (18 leaves) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Revelation and prophecy on war given December 25, 1332", (10 leaves) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "Revelation 22a", n.d.; (3 leaves) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Riches", n.d.; (1 piece) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "Roberts on inspiration", n.d.; (6 leaves) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Science and Mormonism", (57 leaves) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "A shocking homoside (sic)", n.d.; (9 leaves) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "A simple theorem", n.d.; (2 leaves) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "A suggestion worth $1,000,000 to the Church", n.d.; (4 leaves) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "Testimony", November 15, 1925; (1 piece) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - "Unreasonable history of the Book of Mormon", n.d.; 4 different copies, 99 leaves) (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - "Wanted on the other side", n.d.; (1 leaf) (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Was Mormonism revealed? Or did it evolve?", n.d.; (7 leaves) (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - "What would you think?", n.d.; (2 leaves) (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - "Which? Mormon veracity or Mormon mendacity?", (1 piece) (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - "Who should have this magazine and why?", (2 leaves) (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - "A word with non-Mormons", n.d.; (9 leaves) (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous notes and memoranda, (11 pieces) (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Notebook, "Lamoni Call's Compendium of the Doctrines of the Gospel", 1884[?]; (105pp., some unused) (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Card file of notes re various subjects relevant to Call's research, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Printed Items - Lamoni Call, (3 folders)
  - 2000 changes in the Book of Mormon. Bountiful, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - The Anti-Mormon (vol.1, no.2-4). Bountiful, May 1899-April 1902 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Evidence not slander (vol.1). Science and Mormonism. Salt Lake City, February 1926 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Printed Items, Marked or Annotated by Lamoni Call, (4 folders and 27 volumes)
  - Book of Commandments for the Government of the Church of Christ. W.W. Phelps & Company, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - 19 pamphlets re Mormonism, 1920-1931 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - 27 books (Box 3, Box 4)
    Scope and Contents note
    Including:
    - The story of the Mormons. New York: MacMillan, 1923 (Box 3)
    - Science and belief in God. Salt Lake City: The Deseret News, 1924 (Box 3)
    - A series of pamphlets on the Doctrines of the gospel. Salt Lake City: Juvenile Instructor office, 1884 (Box 3)
    - A dictionary of the Book of Mormon. Salt Lake City: Joseph Hyrum Parry, 1891 (Box 3)
    - The myth of the "Manuscript Found". Salt Lake City: Juvenile Instructor office, 1853 (Box 3)
    - History of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latterday Saints (vol.1-2). Salt Lake City: The Desert News, 1902-1904 (Box 3)
    - Biographical sketches of Joseph Smith ... Liverpool: S.W. Richards for Orson Pratt, 1953 (Box 3)
    - The Rocky Mountain Saints. Salt Lake City, Shepherd Book Company, 1904 (Box 3)
    - History of Utah (vol.1-2). Salt Lake City: George Q. Cannon & Sons Company, 1892-1893 (Box 4)
- Unmarked Items
  - Miscellaneous books about Mormonism, (16 items) (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous pamphlets, broadsheets and newspapers, almost all re Mormonism, (57 items) (Box 5)
- Periodicals
  - The People's Press, 1921-1925 (Box 5)
    vol.24, no.10 (December 1921).
    vol.27, no.9 (November 1924).
    vol.28, no.5 (July 1925).
  - Light on Mormonism, 1922-1933 (Box 5)
    vol.1-10. (1922-March 1932) bound together.
    vol.11, no.2-3 (July-December 1932).
    vol.12, no.1 (June 1933).
  - The New Era, a periodical dedicated to the interest of Zion and her cause, 1931-1933 (Box 5)
    Preliminary issue and no.1-12, and 17 (May 1931-May 1932 and February-March 1933).
    Prospectus 1921, and Bulletin, April 1932 for same.